Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XII. Arts Material, 1918-1955
  - Arts Material: Oversize
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (G), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (H-K), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (L-M), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (N-R), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (S), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 13)
    - Clippings and Reprints: European and American Painting and Sculpture (T-Z), 1937-1947 (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - Photographs: Early Christian Sculpture and Architecture, undated (Box 39, Folder 15)
- Series XIII. Chronology Files, 1920-1957
  Art exhibition catalogues, theatre programs, clippings, bills, receipts, correspondence, graphic materials and printed matter collected by Ernie O'Malley and organized chronologically by his son, Cormac O'Malley. Items in this series document his routine activities, and some expenses, as well as, many of friends and associates. A number of the items in this series are photocopies of originals housed elsewhere in the collection, but left here for handy chronological reference.
  - Chronology Files: Index, 2010 (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - 1920-1923 (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - 1922 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - 1923 (Box 21, Folder 24)
    Includes a list of prisoners transferred from Montjoy to Kilmhainham Jail.
  - 1924 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - 1925 (Box 21, Folder 26)
    Includes University College Dublin Sinn Fein card signed by Ernie O'Malley.
  - 1926 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - 1927 (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - 1928 (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - 1928-1935 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - 1929 (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - 1930 (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - 1931 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - 1932 (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - 1933 (Box 21, Folder 35)
  - 1934 (Box 21, Folder 36)
    Includes New York University lectures given at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - 1935 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - 1936: Letters to Ernie O'Malley (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - 1936 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Includes original poems by Ernie O'Malley submitted to The Dublin Magazine.
  - 1937: I (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - 1937: II (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - 1938 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 1939 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - 1940 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - 1941 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - 1942 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - 1943 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - 1944 (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - 1945 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - 1946 (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - 1947: I (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - 1947: II (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - 1948 (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - 1949 (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - 1950 (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - 1951 (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - 1952 (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - 1953 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - 1954 (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - 1955 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - 1956 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - 1957 (includes clippings of death notice, funeral) (Box 22, Folder 26)
- Series XIV. Subject Files, 1922-2008
  Series is arranged alphabetically.
  The bulk of this series consists of research notes and correspondence between Cormac O'Malley and individuals, organizations and institutions associated with his father. Other items include correspondence, clippings, brochures, photographs, greeting cards, interview transcripts, audio reels, printed matter and other ephemeral material pertaining to topics or people associated with Ernie O'Malley or his son, Cormac O'Malley. Throughout the course of his research on his father, Cormac O'Malley worked with his father's friends and their descendents, as well as, numerous universities, libraries, biographers and documentary film makers. In 1970, Cormac O'Malley conducted a series of interviews with Madge and Jack Comer, Sigle Humphreys, Thomas and Peggy Malone, Sean Lemass, Peadar O'Donnell and George Gilmore documenting personal accounts and the military experiences of Ernie O'Malley. The transcriptions of these interviews, as well as, three 1/4" audio reels are housed within this series. Of special interest are materials collected by Ernie O'Malley relating to the Irish Press detailing his travels and expenses, in addition to, the funds he raised for the newspaper. Many of the items in this series are photocopies of originals housed elsewhere in the collection.
  - Subject Files: Indices (14 and 14A), 2010 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Aiken, Frank, 1982-2005 (Box 22, Folder 28)
  - American Indian Dance Festivals, circa 1929 (Box 22, Folder 28A)
    General
    Handwritten lists of American Indian dance festivals, including year, location, and tribe. On verso are drafts of various poems.
  - Andrews, C.S., 2004-2005 (Box 22, Folder 29)
  - Ballads, 1973-2009 (Box 22, Folder 30)
  - Basques, 1926, 1975-2005 (Box 22, Folder 31)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1983-1995 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Behan, Anthony, 2003-2005 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Book Reviews, 2002-2003 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Brady, Kathleen (Kay), 2006-2008 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Brennan, Maureen, 1993-2004, 2008 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Brennan, Robert, 2008 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), 1980-1983 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Paddy (Padraig de Brun), Monsignor, 1935-2000 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Brugha, Cathal and Ruari Brugha, 2005, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Butler, Pat (RTE Ballyseedy), 1997-1998 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Cashman, Seamus (Liam O'Flaherty), Jan 2008 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine): I, 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine): II, 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine): III (photocopies of letters), 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Chronology of Ernie O'Malley 1914-1924 (prepared by Cormac O'Malley), 1982-2003 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Citkowitz-Liber, Rebecca, 1947-2006 (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - Clark, Jack: items purchased by EOM in 1955, circa 2003 (Box 23, Folder 17)
  - Clifford-Comer, Madge (assistant to Ernie O'Malley), steno notebooks, circa 1935-1947 (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - Clurman, Harold, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 19)
  - Coffey, Donogh, 1972-1984 (Box 23, Folder 20)
  - Comer Family, 1922-2005 (Box 23, Folder 21)
  - Comerford, Judge James J., 1983 (Box 23, Folder 22)
  - Cooney, Andy, 2004-2006 (Box 23, Folder 23)
  - Craig, Maurice, 2007 (Box 23, Folder 24)
  - Crane, Hart, 1931-2008 (Box 23, Folder 25)
  - Davis, Chester (of Simpson, Thatcher and Barlett, attorneys) corrsepondence to Helen Hooker O'Malley, 1956 (Box 23, Folder 26)
  - DeValera, Eamon, 1945-2004 (Box 23, Folder 27)
  - Dictionary of Irish Biography, 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 28)
    See also Cooney, Andy
  - Dodge-Luhan, Mabel (Luhan, Mabel Dodge, New Mexico), 2005 (Box 23, Folder 29)
  - Fitzgerald, Mabel (Mrs. Desmond), 2002-2003 (Box 23, Folder 30)
  - Folklore (on Ernie O'Malley), 2003-2006 (Box 23, Folder 31)
  - Ford, John (Jack) and family, 1951-1985 (Box 23, Folder 32)
  - Gallagher, Frank and Anne, 1957-2004 (Box 23, Folder 33)
  - Gallivan, Thomas and Family, 1922-2004 (Box 23, Folder 34)
    Surname also spelled Galivan.
  - Goddard, Theodora, 1983-2004 (Box 23, Folder 35)
  - Golden, Helen Merriman and Eithne Golden-Sax, 1928-2005 (Box 23, Folder 36)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters: I, 1928-2005 (Box 23, Folder 37)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters: II, 1928-2005 (Box 23, Folder 38)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters: I (typed copies of letters), 1928-2005 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Golden Family: Ernie O'Malley Letters: II (typed copies of letters), 1928-2005 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Golden Family, 1926-2002 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Golden Family, 1926-2002 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Golden, E / O'Malley, Cormac, 1930-2002 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Golden-Katz, Deidre, 1982-1984 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Golden-Sax, Eithne (mostly clippings), 1957-2006 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Greene, Graham, 1947-2006 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Greene, Graham: Clippings, 1989-2006 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Greenwood, Marion, 1930, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Marion Greenwood (1909-1970) - New York artist who did a portrait of Ernie O'Malley circa 1933.
  - Halligan-Clarke, Sunniva, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Henry, Paul, 2007 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Herbert, Robert (Limerick Public Library), 1948-1955 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Holloway, Joseph, 1941 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Hone, Evie, 1945-1985 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Houghton Miflin Company, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Hughes, John T. and Mary (sister), 1938-1948 (Box 24, Folder 17)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue), 1922-1931, 1970-2003, undated (Box 24, Folder 18)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue): additional copies, 1922-2003, undated (Box 24, Folder 19)
  - Interviews (typed and audio): Cormac O'Malley, Madge Clifford Comer, Jack Comer, Single Humphreys, Sean Lemass, Tom and Peggy Malone, Peader O'Donnell, and George Gilmore (includes 3 reels at end of series), Oct 1970 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  - Irish Pension Board, 2007-2008 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  - Irish Press, Limited: I, 1928-1931, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  - Irish Press, Limited: II, 1928-1931, 1974 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Irish Times, 1922, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 24)
  - Jeffers, Una and Robinson, 1928, 1993-2006 (Box 24, Folder 25)
  - Johnson, Walter Willard "Spud", 2004 (Box 24, Folder 26)
  - Joyce-O'Loughlin, Una: letters to EOM and COM, 1964-1985 (Box 24, Folder 27)
  - Kazan, Elia, 2003 (Box 24, Folder 28)
  - Kelleher, John V., 1989, 2001-2002 (Box 24, Folder 29)
  - Kelly, Grace V. (art critic), 1929-1950 (Box 24, Folder 30)
  - Kelly, P.J., 1978-1984 (Box 24, Folder 31)
  - Kerrigan, Georgette and Sarsfield, 1937-2004 (Box 24, Folder 32)
  - Kerwood, Beatrice, 2005 (Box 24, Folder 33)
  - Killanin, Lord Michael, 1982-1984 (Box 24, Folder 34)
  - Kilmainham Jail: I, 1921-1991, undated (Box 24, Folder 35)
  - Kilmainham Jail: II, 1921-1991, undated (Box 24, Folder 36)
  - Kilmainham Jail Museum and Exhibit: I, 1987-2003 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Kilmainham Jail Museum and Exhibit: II, 1998-2007 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Lavin, Mary, 1983-1985 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Le Brocquy, Louis and Family, 1946-1973 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Lemass, Sean, Oct 1970 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Lennon, Joseph, 2000 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Macardle, Dorothy, 1946 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - MacBride, Sean, 1922-1923, 1974-2005 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - MacCarvill, Niall and Eileen McGrane, 1970-1999 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - MacEvilly, Michael, 2006-2008 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas: I, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas: II, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas: III, 1947-2007 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - MacHale, Desmond (The Quiet Man film; handwritten bio of Ernie O'Malley), 1973-2008 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - MacLochlainn, S.D. (nephew of Sean Connolly), 1985 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - MacNiece, Frederick Louis, 2006 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Magan, Manchan / Roan / Croine ("The Struggle"): I, 1973-2005 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Magan, Manchan / Roan / Croine ("The Struggle"): II, 1973-2005 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Maguire, Tom and Family, 2004 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Malone, Thomas and Peggy (contemporary of Ernie O'Malley), Oct 1970 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Manahan, Liam and family, 1983-2007 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Martin, Colbert, 1963-1985 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - McGahern, John, 2002-2006 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - McGlynn, Mick, 1964, 1983 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - McGrail, Jean: I, 1978-1983 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - McGrail, Jean: II, 1978-1983 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - McHugh, Roger and Patricia, 1927-1945 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - McKay, Francis: I (Republican material), 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - McKay, Francis: II, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - McKay, Francis: III, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - McKay, Francis: IV, 1984-2004 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  - Meehan, Bernard (Trinity College Library, Manuscripts division), 1989-1991 (Box 25, Folder 33)
  - Metzner, Wolfgang (son of Alfred Metzner, publisher of On Another Man's Wound in German), 1982-1989 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Military Archives, 1922-1923, 2003 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Monroe, Harriet (Poetry Magazine), 1935 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - National Archives of Ireland, 1922-2001 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - National Library of Ireland, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Neenan, Connie (Cornelius), 1972-1984 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Letters relationg to Ernie O'Malley: I (compiled by Cormac O'Malley and copied elsewhere in the collection), 1926, 1949-1989 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Letters relationg to Ernie O'Malley: II (compiled by Cormac O'Malley and copied elsewhere in the collection), 1926, 1949-1989 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry (TG4 documentary), 2006 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: I, 2007 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: II, 2007 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry, 2008 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: Film Proposal/Drafts: I, 2006-2007 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - O'Callaghan, Jerry: Film Proposal / Drafts: II, 2006-2007 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  - O'Connor, Frank [Michael O'Dohoun], 1998-2007 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  - O'Connor, Ulick, circa 1991 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  - O'Doherty, Joseph (O'Doherty v. O'Malley, copy of judgment), 1937 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  - O'Donnell, James, Jul 193-Aug 1983 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  - O'Donnell, Peadar (interview by Cormac O'Malley, also with George Gilmore), 1970-1986 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  - O'Dowd, John David, 1985-1986 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  - O'Faolain, Sean, 1983-2004 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  - O'Flaherty, Liam, 1983-2004 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  - O'hAodna, Michael, circa 1950, undated (Box 26, Folder 24)
  - O'Malley, Ernie: I (photocopies of letters), 1930-1955 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  - O'Malley, Ernie: II (photocopies of letters), 1930-1955 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - O'Rahilly, Aodogan "The Flight in Ailesbury Road" recollection, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - O'Reilly, Martin, 1973-1984 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - O'Sullivan, Sean [portrait], 1941 (Box 26, Folder 28A)
  - Piper, John, 1998-2006 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - Plunkett, Countess (Mary Josephine), 1991 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - Poetry Magazine (Chicago), 1933-2004 (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - Proud, Ernest W., 1931 (Box 26, Folder 32)
  - Publications (by Ernie O'Malley): I, 1940-1963 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  - Publications (by Ernie O'Malley): II, 1940-1963 (Box 26, Folder 34)
  - Radio Telefis Eireann, 1982-2008 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  - Raleigh, John, 1939-2008 (Box 26, Folder 36)
  - References to Ernie O'Malley - in books, articles and publications: I, 1936-2006, undated (Box 26, Folder 37)
  - References to Ernie O'Malley - in books, articles and publications: II, 1936-2006, undated (Box 26, Folder 38)
  - Reynolds, Lorna, 1983-2003 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    Lorna Reynolds (1911-2003) - author
  - Robinson, Lennox, 1967, 2005-2006 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Rogers, Fanny, 1974, 1982 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    New York artist and literary figure.
  - Rothenstein, John (Director of Tate Gallery, London), 1946, 2006-2008 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Russell, Sean, Sep 13, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Ryan, Desmond (author), 1984-2003 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Sheehan, Eugene "Gene", 1983 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    Owner of undertaker business in Boston and close friend of Eamon de Valera.
  - Sheehy, Michael, 1940-1952, 1985 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Christy and Anne, 1959, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Somerville-Large, Sammy, 1950, 2004 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Stewart, Dorothy, circa 1956 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Strand, Paul: I, 1921-2008 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Strand, Paul: II, 1921-2008 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Stuart, Francis, 1983-2000 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson and Laura: I, 1945-2008 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson and Laura: II, 1945-2008 (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Sykes, Gerald, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 17)
  - Tobin, Marion, 1986-2005, undated (Box 27, Folder 18)
  - Truden, Bernardine, 1964 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    Journalist for the Boston Globe and member of Eire Society of Boston.
  - University College Cork Archives (Catriona Mulcahy), 2005 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  - University College Dublin Archives, circa 2003 (Box 27, Folder 21)
  - Varney, John (New York University), 1934-1935 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - Villard, Marquita, 1933-2007 (Box 27, Folder 23)
  - Wall, Mervyn (Radio Eireann), 1972-1984 (Box 27, Folder 24)
  - Walsh, Frank P., 1929 (Box 27, Folder 25)
    Irish American lawyer in New York City.
  - Walsh, Roisin (Chief Librarian, City of London Public Library); family, 1930s, 2004 (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Walston, Catherine and Henry, 1935-2007 (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Weston, Edward, 1969-2003, undated (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - White, James, 1983-1984 (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - Whittlesey, Eunice Stoddard Smith (Mrs. Julian H.), 1983-2004 (Box 27, Folder 30)
    Actress with The Group Theatre.
  - Yaddo Foundation: I, 1955, 1983-1999 (Box 27, Folder 31)
  - Yaddo Foundation: II, 1955, 1983-1999 (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Yeats, Jack B. (lists, notes), undated (Box 27, Folder 33)
  - Young, Ella, 2008 (Box 27, Folder 34)
  - Trinity College - Microfilm of Childers Correspondence, Manuscript Department; Manuscript: 7850/885-911 (copies available in Series under Childers), 1923-1924 (Box 29)
  - Interviews: 3 reel tapes. 2. EOM, Conn Ranger; 4: Comer, Jack and Madge; 5. Thomas and Peggy Malone (Sean Ford), Madge Clifford Comer, Jack Comer., 1970 (Box 29)
- Series XV. Printed Ephemera, 1789-1950
  The items are arranged in alphabetical order with original inventory numbers included on the folders.
  Items in this series reflect O'Malley's varied interests in Irish history, cartography, art and many other areas and include prints, reprints, maps, photographs, essays, brochures, letters, drawings, reproductions and other ephemeral materials and artifacts collected or inherited by Ernie O'Malley. While most of the graphic items in this series are reprints or reproductions, several original cards, drawings and paintings from notable artists including Roy Boynton, and Jack Hanlon are also included. Nearly twenty maps and nine letters either written by or addressed to historically significant Irishmen and women including Eva Gore Booth, Standish O' Grady, Sean O'Sullivan and Thomas Grattan complete the series as well as an undated historic account of the Spanish Armada's landing and an indenture for land dated 1857.
  - Printed Ephemera Index, 2010 (Box 27, Folder 35)
  - Account: "Spanish Fleet Landing in Kinsdale, Ireland in 1601" handwritten, [John Blake Dillon?], undated (Box 27, Folder 36)
  - "Adventures in Music" [Orchestral Concert Series], 1946 (Box 42, Folder 23)
  - Applegood, Frank G.: "Domingo" photocopy of engraving; Taos, NM, pre 1932 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - "The Blasket Island from Dun Quin" (print of woodcut), undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Christmas card by Jack Hanlon, signed by artist, circa 1945 (Box 27, Folder 40)
  - Christmas card signed by Jack B. Yeats (photocopy), circa 1948-1949 (Box 27, Folder 41)
  - Christmas card; signed "to Ernie from Katherine", circa 1933 (Box 27, Folder 42)
  - Clarke, Austin: pencil drawing, reproduction, 1924 (Box 27, Folder 43)
  - County Cork: essay, manuscript on, undated (Box 27, Folder 47)
  - DeValera, Eamon: print of portrait, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - DeValera, Eamon "Taioseach's Broadcast to the Nation" delivered May 16, 1945; reprint from the Irish Press, May 17, 1945 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Do Bhaucaillibh augus Callinibh na h-Eireann, 1926 (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - Early Irish History and Kingship: essay, manuscript on, undated (Box 27, Folder 48)
  - Frost, Stella: Landscape (photoprint), circa 1947 (Box 27, Folder 72)
  - Gore, Booth, Eva: Correspondence to Seamus O'Sullivan, undated (Box 27, Folder 49)
  - Gore, Booth, Eva: Correspondence to W. Russell, undated (Box 27, Folder 50)
  - Grattan, Henry: letter, Apr 5, 1789 (Box 27, Folder 51)
  - The Gypsy cover woodcut by Alan Odle, 1916 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Harvard Univeristy official register: Courses and Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1928-1929 (Box 27, Folder 69)
  - Horgan, Paul: "Cathedral Altar" reprints, woodcut, circa 1945-1950 (Box 27, Folder 74)
  - "The Hurricane" poem by Hart Crane on his personal stationery) typescript, Jan 1931 (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Indenture (vellum) "Conveyance of a piece of land" in Charlott St, Leister, England; Rev. William Tiptaft to Willaim Tomblin Keal, Esq., 1857 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - John F. Kennedy Ireland Visit Commemorative Booklet, 1963 (Box 42, Folder 24)
  - Jones, Colonel Edward: essay on, late 1800s (Box 27, Folder 46)
  - "La Dame Fantome" and "De Mieux en Mieux", 1922 (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - Lawrence, D.H. photocopy of [wood]print of head, circa 1950s (Box 27, Folder 75)
  - "Literature of the Graveyard," Jean-Paul Satre, Francois Mauriac, Andre Malraux, Arthur Koestler, 1948 (Box 42, Folder 22)
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge: drawing of home in Taos, NM ("Los Gallos"), circa 1929 (Box 27, Folder 45)
  - Mahony, Francis: Correspondence to Crofton Coker, Oct 31, 1841 (Box 27, Folder 52)
  - Manuscript: MacDareo's "Noshel" (Fermoy and Ballymole Books), circa late 1800s, undated (Box 27, Folder 37)
  - Map: "A Plan and a section of the River Nore from City of Kilkenny to the town of Enniscorthy with elevations of Kilkenny canal", circa late 1800s (Box 27, Folder 67)
  - Map: Ancient Map of Irish Districts in Queen's County and County Kildare (reprint), undated (Box 27, Folder 58)
  - Map: Avignon, France, undated (Box 27, Folder 59)
  - Map: "Cambridge, Sheet 20," Great Britain (signed by Ernie O'Malley), circa 1945-1955 (Box 27, Folder 60)
  - Map: "The Cittie of Limerick from Thomas Pacata's "Pacata Hibernia"" or "A History of the Wars in Ireland during the Reign of Queen Elizabeth (color engraving), 1820 reprint, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Map: Diocese of Tuam, undated (Box 27, Folder 68)
  - Map: France: Michelin Guide to Northern France, undated (Box 27, Folder 61)
  - Map: France, Northwestern (annotated by Ernie O'Malley), undated (Box 27, Folder 66)
  - Map: "Galway the Capital of Connaught in the Kingdom of Ireland, 1651" drawn and engraved, 1820 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Map: Great Western Railway of England: Handbook for Travellers from Overseas, undated (Box 27, Folder 62)
  - Map: Indian and Ceylon, undated (Box 27, Folder 63)
  - Map: Kilkenny; showing seats of original septs and ancient tribe lands, undated (Box 27, Folder 64)
  - Map: La Cote D'Azur (France), circa 1938 (Box 27, Folder 65)
  - Map: "Map of the City of Dublin and Township of Rathmines", 1864 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Map: "Map of Ireland engraved for the Loyal National Repeal Association", circa 1840s (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Map: Mayo, Sheet 67 [Northside of Clew Bay], published by Director General at the Ordinance Survey Office, Phoenix Park, Dublin 1920, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Covers O'Malley's home at Burrishoole Lodge, near Clew Bay, Co. Mayo.
  - Map: "Pictorial Map of Mexico" by Miguel Gomex Median (color reproduction) published by Fischgrund Publishng Co., Mexico (exclusive publishers of Diego River's Frescoes), 1931 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Map: Youghal as in Elizabeth's reign when sacked by the insurgent Earl of Desmond (reprint), undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Mitchel, John: Correspondence to Charles Magee, Dec 24, 1845 (Box 27, Folder 53)
  - Mepsil House Flats brochure (where Ernie O'Malley rented a flat, 1954-1957), circa 1954 (Box 27, Folder 38)
  - O'Grady, Standish: Correspondence to Miss Costello, undated (Box 27, Folder 54)
  - O'Grady, Standish: Correspondence to Mr. Law, undated (Box 27, Folder 55)
  - O'Malley, Ernie: Wallet (used while in New Mexico), 1931 (Box 28, Folder 10)